<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Colonel James Clinton</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <dateline><placeName>Head Quarters, New York,</placeName> July 7, 1776.</dateline>
           <p> Sir: I received yours by <persName>Major Rensselaer</persName> and am pleased to find you are making the necessary
            Preperations to repel the Enemy in Case of an Attack.</p>
           <p> I hope you will be able to get Arms sufficient for the Men under your Command who are destitute;
            but if not, you are to dismiss all those whom you cannot equip. I mean to confine myself to the
            Militia wholly, as it is equally absurd and unjust, to keep Men in continental Pay, who will be of no
            Service in Time of Action, for Want of Arms. It is, in Fact, amusing ourselves with the Appearance of
            strength, when at the same Time we want the Reality.</p>
           <p> Colonel Knox informs me, he has no Carriages to spare; but you can have the Carriage Wheels, which
            with the Iron will be delivered to the Care of <persName>Major Rensselaer.</persName></p>
           <p> As to the Ball for the small Arms, they should be sent, if the Sizes could be ascertained, so as to fit
            the Musquets exactly; but as that cannot be done, I shall order a sufficient Quantity of Lead to be
            sent up, which you will direct to be cast into Balls suitable for your Purpose. You must furnish the
            Bullet Moulds in the best Manner you can, as there are none here.
            With Regard to the Appointment of <persName>Doctor Tappen,</persName> I would just mention, that as it is a Matter
            transacted between you and the Provincial Congress, with which I am quite unconnected, I would
            choose it should continue so. However, by renewing your Application to the Congress, you will
            doubtless receive a satisfactory Answer. I am, etc.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
