<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Wastington's Half-Brother Augustine</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <dateline><placeName>Mount Vernon,</placeName> August 2, 1755.</dateline>
           <p> Dear Brother: The pleasure of your Company at <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> always did, and always will, afford
            me infinite satisfaction; but at this time, I am too truly sensible how needful the Country is of the
            assistance of all its members, to desire to hear that any are absent.53 I most sincerely wish that
            harmony and unanimity may prevail amongst you, and that a happy issue may attend your prudent
            resolutions.</p>
           <p> I am not able were I ever so willing, to meet you in Town, for I assure you it is with some difficulty
            and with fatigue that I visit my Plantation's in the Neck, so much has a sickness of five weeks'
            continuance reduced me: But tho it is not in my power to meet you there, I can nevertheless assure you, and other's (who it may concern to borrow a phrase from 
            Governor Innes) that I am so little dispirited at what has happen'd, that I am always ready and always willing, to do my
            Country any Services that I am capable off; but never upon the Terms I have done, having suffer'd
            much in my private fortune, besides impairing one of the best of Constitution's. I was employ'd to go a journey in the Winter (when I believe few or none wou'd have 
            undertaken it) and what did I get by it? my expenses borne! </p>
           <p> I then was appointed with trifling Pay to conduct
            an handful of Men to the Ohio. What did I get by this? Why, after putting myself to a considerable
            expence in equipping and providing necessarys for the Campaigne I went out, was soundly beaten,
            lost them all—came in, and had my Commission taken from me or, in other words my Corn'd,
            reduced, under pretence of an Order from home. I then went out a Volunteer with Genl. Braddock
            and lost all my Horses and many other things, but this being a voluntary act, I shou'd not have
            mention'd it, was it not to shew that I have been upon the loosing order ever since I enter'd the
            Service, which is now near two year's; so that I think I can't be blare'd, shou'd I, if I leave my Family
            again, end'vt. to do it upon such terms as to prevent my sufferg., (to gain by it, is the least of my ex-
            pectation).</p>
            <p>I doubt not but you have heard the particulars of our shameful defeat, which really was so
            scandalous that I hate to have it mention'd. You desire to know what Artillery was taken in the late
            Engt; it is easily told, we lost all that we carr'd out, save 2 Six pound'rs, and a few Cohorns that were
            left with Colo. Dunbar; and the Cohorns have since been destroy'd to expedate his flight. You also
            ask whether I think the Forces can March this Fall. I must answer, I think it impossible, for them to
            do the French any damage (unless it be by starv'g) for want of a proper Train of Artillery; yet they
            may be very serviceable in erect'g small Fortresses at convenient places to deposit provisions in, by
            which the Country will be eas'd of an immense expence in the Carriage, and it will also be a mean's
            of securing a Retreat if we sh'd be put to the Rout again; the success of this tho' will dep'd gre'tly
            upon what <persName>Gov'r. Shirley </persName>does at <placeName>Niagara,</placeName> for if he succeeds, their Comn. with Canada will be entirely
            stop'd.</p>
           <p> It is impossible for me to guess at the number of recruits that may be want'g, as that must depend
            altogeth'r upon the strength of the French on the Ohio, w'ch to my g't. astonishm't we were ever
            strangers to.</p>
            <p>I thank you very heartily for your kind offer of a Chr. and for your goodness in sending my things;
            and, after begg'g you excuse the imperfect'ns. of the above which in part are owing to hav'g much
            Comp'y that hurrys me I shall conclude Dr. Sir, </p>
            <p>Yr. most Afft. Broth'r.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
