<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to President of Congress</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <dateline> <placeName>Camp Cambridge,</placeName> October 24, 1775.</dateline>
           <p> Sir: My conjecture of the Destination of the late Squadron from <placeName>Boston</placeName> in my last, has been
            unhappily verified, by an outrage exceeding in Barbarity and cruelty every hostile Act practiced
            among civilized nations; I have inclosed the Account given me by <persName>Mr. Jones</persName> a Gentleman of the
            <placeName>Town of Falmouth</placeName> of the Destruction of that flourishing Village. He is a very great sufferer and
            informs me that the Time allowed for the removal of Effects was so small, that valuable Property of
            all kinds and to a great amount has been destroyed.</p>
            <p> The Orders shewn by the Captain for this horred proceedure, by which it appears the same
            desolation is meditated upon all the <placeName>Towns on the Coast,</placeName> made it my Duty to communicate it as
            quickly and extensively as possible. As <placeName>Portsmouth</placeName> was the next place to which he proposed to go,
            General Sullivan was permitted to go up and give them his Assistance and advice to ward off the
            Blow. I flatter myself the like Event will not happen there, as they have 
            a Fortification of some strength and a Vessel has arrived at a place called Sheepscott with 1500 lb of Powder.</p>
            <p> The Gentlemen of the Congress have nearly finished their Business, but as they write by this
            Opportunity, I must beg leave to refer you to their Letters for what concerns their Commission.
            We have had no Occurrence of any Consequence in the Camp, since I had the Honor of Addressing
            you last. I am Yours</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
