<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="../WashLetterTEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!-- Wrong Syntax-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Governor Nicholas Cooke</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <orgName>Cambridge,</orgName><dateline> March 17, 1776.</dateline>
           <p> Sir: I have the Pleasure to inform you, that this morning the Ministerial Troops evacuated the <placeName>Town of
            Boston,</placeName> without destroying it and that we are now in the full possession; upon which event, I beg leave to Congratulate you, and sincerely wish, if the 
            Ministry persevere in the same unconstitution and despotic measures, which too long have marked their conduct, that our opposition and
            resistance, in every Quarter, may be crowned with the success they have been here. Where their destination is, or what plans they have in view, is altogether unknown; 
            most probably the next attempt will be against <placeName>New York,</placeName> or some more <placeName>Southern Colony.</placeName></p>
            <p>However, I should think, tho' I do not believe they have any design against <placeName>Rhode Island,</placeName> that it will be adviseable to keep a
            strict look out; and submit it to you, whether it may not be proper against the time you apprehend
            they might arrive, to call in a number of the Militia and have them posted in proper places. I do not
            mean to direct the Measure, but only to mention It for your Consideration; to me it appears worthy
            of attention. I am Yours.
            N. B. <dateline>March 19th,</dateline> the Fleet is still in <placeName>King and Nantasket Roads.</placeName></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
