<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<?xml-model href="../ODD/out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Washington's Brother Jack</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p><placeName>Camp at Will's Creek,</placeName> <date>June 7, 1755.</date></p>
            <p>Dear <persName>Jack</persName>: As much hurried as I am at present, I can't think of leaving this place without writing to
            you; tho' I have no time to be particular. I was Escorted by 8 Men of the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Militia</orgName> from <location><settlement>Winchester</settlement></location> to
            this place; which 8 Men were 2 Days assembling; but I believe they wou'd not have been more than
            as many seconds dispersing if I had been attacked. Upon arrival here, I found <persName>Sir Jno. St. Clair</persName>
            with a body of 500 Men were March'd to prepare the Roads, lay a deposit of Provisions at the little
            Meadows, and to erect some kind of defensive work there.</p>
            <p>To morrow <persName>Sir Peter</persName> with the first <orgName type="#military">Brigade</orgName>, begin their March, and on Monday the General and the 2d. will follow. We have no certain acct. from 
            the Ohio: but have advices from <location><settlement>Philadelphia</settlement></location> that a body of 300 F. pass'd Oswego on their way to <location><settlement>Fort Duquisne,</settlement></location> and
            that a larger Detachment was hourly expected. A Captn. of <persName>Sir Peter's </persName>Regim't with several of the
            common Soldiers of the different Corps has died since our Incampm't here, and many others are
            now sick with a kind of bloody Flux. I wrote from <location><settlement>Winchester</settlement></location> a Letter which I hope you have receiv'd
            and shou'd be glad of an answer as soon as possible; any Letter's to me, directed to the care of <persName>Mr.
            Cox,</persName> at <location><settlement>Winchester,</settlement></location> will be certain of a conveyance I am <persName>Dr. Jack</persName> Yr. most Affe. Brother
         </p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
