<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../ODD/out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Washington's Friend Robert Jackson</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written by George Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p><location><settlement>Mount Vernon,</settlement></location> <date>August 2, 1755.</date></p>
            <p>Dr. Sir: I must acknowledge you had great reason to be terrified with the first acc'ts, that was given
            of our unhappy defeat, and I must own, I was not a little surpris'd to find that <persName>Governor Innis</persName> was
            the means of alarming the Country with a report of that extraordinary nature, without having
            any better confirmation of the truth, than an affrighted waggoner's story. Its true, we have been
            beaten, most shamefully beaten, by a handful of Men ! who only intended to molest and disturb
            our March; Victory was their smallest expectation, but see the wondrous works of Providence! the
            uncertainty of Human things! We, but a few moments before, believ'd our number's almost equal
            to the <orgName type="#military">Canadian Force;</orgName> they only expected to annoy us. </p>
           <p> Yet, contrary to all expectation and human probability, and even to the common course of things, we were totally defeated, sustain'd the loss
            of every thing; which they have got, are enrichen'd and strengthened by it. This, as you observe, must be an affecting story to the Colony; and will, no doubt, 
            license the tongues of People to censure those they think most blamably; which by the by, often falls very wrongfully. I join very heartily with
            you in believing that when this story comes to be related in future Annals, it will meet with ridicule or in
            dignation; for had I not been witness to the fact on that fatal Day, I sh'd scarce give credit to it now.</p>
           <p> Whenever it suits you to come into Fairfax I hope you will make your home at <location><settlement>Mount Vernon.</settlement></location>
            Please to give my Compts. to all inquiring Friends; and I assure you, nothing cou'd have added
            greater satisfaction to my safe return, than hearing of the friendly concern that was express'd on my
            suppos'd Death. I am, Yours.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
