<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="../WashLetterTEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!-- Wrong Syntax-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Commissioners of D.C</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <orgName>Philadelphia,</orgName><dateline>August 20, 1793.</dateline>
            <p>Gentlemen: This will be handed to you by <persName>Mr. James Greenleaf,</persName> a native of <placeName>Boston,</placeName> who has resided
            for some years past in Amsterdam, and has lately been appointed Consul for the U. S. at that place.
            This Gentleman, I understand, has it in contemplation to make certain proposals to you for building
            a number of houses in the <orgName>Federal City,</orgName> provided he can have lots upon such terms and conditions
            as may correspond with his interest in the undertaking while it tends, at the same time, to promote
            the great object of the city. I am pursuaded, Gentlemen, that you will listen with attention and weigh
            with candour any proposals that may promise to promote the growth of the City in the degree that <persName>Mr. Greenleaf's</persName> undertaking upon the extensive
            Scale that it has been represented to me, would do. But it will lay with yourselves to decide how far
            the state of your funds will justify you closing with any proposals that may not tend to give them an
            immediate increase.</p>
            <p>It will undoubtedly be essential to <persName>Mr. Greenleaf</persName> that you should be impressed with just ideas
            with regard to his means of insuring the punctual performance of any engagements he may enter
            into, with you (if you shd. come upon any terms with him), and he will therefore undoubtedly take
            measures to satisfy you on this head. He has been represented to me as a Gentleman of large property and having the command of much money in this Country and in 
            Europe; but I can say nothing on this head from my own knowledge. Having had occasion to make enquiry respecting him
            before his appointment to the office of Consul, the Accounts which I received were highly favourable
            to <persName>Mr. Greenleaf,</persName> both as to the respectability of his connections in this Country and in <placeName>Holland</placeName>
            (where he married), and as to his own character. And I have reason to believe that if you can find
            it consistent with your duty to the public to attach <persName>Mr. Greenleaf</persName>to the <orgName>Federal City,</orgName> he will be a
            valuable acquisition. I am Yours
         </p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
