<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../ODD/out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to the Recruiting Officers of the Virgina Regiment</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written By Greoge Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the Library of Congress</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p><placeName>[Williamsburg],</placeName> <date>September [3], 1755.</date></p>
            <p n="1">First; That each Captain shall, by beat of Drum or otherwise, Raise Thirty men; Each Lieutenant
            Eighteen; and each Ensign, Twelve men.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly: That each Captain shall appoint proper Persons to act as non-commissioned Officers,
            during their Recruiting Service: But those non-commissioned Officers, so appointed, are not to be
            confirmed, 'till approved of by me, or a Field Officer for that purpose.</p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly: That no Officer shall list any Men under Sixteen, or above Fifty years of age: Nor are they to
            list men under five feet four Inches high, unless they are well made, strong, and active; then, and in
            that case, they will be received.
            Neither are they to list any men who have old Sores upon their legs, or who are subject to Fits; which
            will be inspected into by the Surgeons, upon their arrival at Quarters: and such as are found to come
            under these Articles, will be discharged; and the Officers have no allowance made.</p>
            <p n="4">Fourthly: That, when each Recruiting Officer has listed his Complement of Men, he is immediately to
            repair to the Place of Rendezvouz; which I hope, and expect, will be by the first day of October next:
            but if in case the whole should not be complete by that time; it is then my Orders, that each Captain
            shall forthwith send one of his Subalterns with all the Recruits, to the quarters assigned him, and remain with the other Subaltern to complete 
            his Company, with all imaginable Diligence. There will be a Field Officer to receive, review, and examine the Recruits
            that are brought in; who will have power to reject and discharge, such as come under the above
            Articles.</p>
           <p n="5">Fifthly: That, for each Recruit that is passed by such Field Officer, the Officer who Listed him, shall
            receive two Pistoles, and an allowance of eight-pence per Day for Subsistance, from the day of his
            attestation, to the day of his being received into the Regiment.</p>
           <p n="6">Sixthly: That all Recruits, so soon as they are Listed, are to take the Oaths provided for that purpose;
            which is to be attested by the Magistrate who administered them.
            Their Stature, Complexion, and so forth, is to be taken also, and entered by the Recruiting Officer in a
            Book kept for that purpose.</p>
           <p n="7">Seventhly: That no Officer shall bring in any charge against his Men for Necessaries; Each man being
            to receive full Clothing, on his arrival at the place of Rendezvous.
            Lastly: That when you are on the Recruiting Service, and on your March; you are to observe the same
            good Order and Discipline, as in Camp or in Quarters; and you are to conform yourself, in every
            respect, to the Rules and Articles of War. Given under my hand etc.
            All the Officers then present received the foregoing Instructions, and money for Recruiting; and
            some of them were appointed to act 'till further Orders, as followeth:
           <persName> Viz. To Captain Spotswoods Company,</persName>
           <persName>Lieutenant Lomax</persName> and <persName>Ensign Garter,</persName> were ordered to do Duty as Subalterns: and to
           <persName> Captain Harrison;</persName> <persName>Lieutenant John. Hall;</persName><persName> Ensign Nathaniel Thompson. </persName>
           <persName>To Captain Lewis;</persName> <persName>Lieutenant Peter Steenbergen;</persName> <persName>Ensign Edward Hubard.</persName> 
           <persName> To Captain Peachy,</persName>  <persName>Lieutenant John Williams;</persName> <persName>Ensign William Dangerfield.</persName>
           <persName>To Captain Bell,</persName> <persName>Lieutenant John Campbell;</persName> <persName>Ensign William Fleming. </persName>
           <persName>To Captain McKenzie,</persName> <persName>Lieutenant James Baker,</persName> <persName>Ensign Leonard Price.</persName>
            And were ordered by their Instructions, to Rendezvous as followeth: 
            <placeName>Fredericksburgh;</placeName><persName> Captain Spotswood,</persName> and Company, <persName>Captain Harrison,</persName> and Company,<persName> Captain Lewis,</persName>
            and Company. 
            <placeName>Winchester;</placeName> <persName>Captain Bell,</persName> and Company; <placeName>Alexandria;</placeName> <persName>Captain Peachy,</persName> and Company;
            <persName>Captain McKenzie,</persName> and Company.
            The other Subalterns then present, videlicet; 
            <persName>Lieutenant's Brockenbrough,</persName> <persName> Lowry</persName> and<persName> King:</persName>
            <persName>Ensigns Millner,</persName><persName> Dean</persName> and <persName>Weedon;</persName> who were not appointed to any particular Companies, were
            ordered to Rendezvous at <placeName>Fredericksburg;</placeName> <persName>Lieutenant Lowry;</persName> <persName>Ensign Weedon;</persName> <placeName>Alexandria;</placeName> <persName>Lieutenant Brockenbrough,</persName>
            <persName>Lieutenant John King,</persName> <persName>Ensign John Dean.
        </persName>
           </p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
