<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../ODD/out/GeoWash.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diary Entry</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Written by George Washington</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Washington Diary Entries May 1781</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><date> May 1781</date></p>
         
         <p>I begin, at this Epoch, a concise Journal of <orgName type="#USmilitary">Military</orgName> transactions &amp;ca;. I lament not having attempted it from the commencement of the War, in aid of my memory and wish the multiplicity of matter which continually surround me and the embarrassed State of our affairs which is momently calling the attention to perplexities of one kind or another, may not defeat altogether or so interrupt my present intention, &amp; plan, as to render it of little avail.</p>
         <p>To have the clearer understanding of the entries which may follow, it would be proper to recite, in detail, our wants and our prospects but this alone would be a Work of much time, and great magnitude. It may suffice to give the sum of them—wch., I shall do in a few words—viz.—</p>
         <p>Instead of having Magazines filled with provisions, we have a scanty pittance scattered here &amp; there in the different States. Instead of having our Arsenals well supplied with <orgName type="#USmilitary">Military</orgName> Stores, they are poorly provided, &amp; the Workmen all leaving them. Instead of having the various articles of Field equipage in readiness to deliver, the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Quarter Master General</roleName> (as the denier resort, according to his acct.) is but now applying to the several States to provide these things for their <orgName type="#USmilitary">Troops</orgName> respectively. Instead of having a regular System of transportation established upon credit or funds in the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Qr. Masters</roleName> hands to defray the contingent Expences of it, we have neither the one nor the other and all that business, or a great part of it, being done by <orgName type="#USmilitary">Military</orgName> Impress, we are daily &amp; hourly oppressing the people—souring their tempers and alienating their affection. Instead of having the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Regiments</orgName> compleated to the New establishment (and which ought to have been So by the [      ] of [      ] agreeably to the requisitions of <orgName type="#political">Congress</orgName>, scarce any State in the <orgName type="#political">Union</orgName> has, at this hour, an eighth part of its quota in the field and little prospect, that I can see, of ever getting more than half. In a word—instead of having everything in readiness to take the Field, we have nothing—and instead of having the prospect of a glorious offensive campaign before us, we have a bewildered, and gloomy defensive one—unless we should receive a powerful aid of Ships—Land Troops and [357] Money from our generous allies &amp; these, at present, are too contingent to build upon.</p>
         <p><date>May 1st</date>. Induced by pressing necessity—the inefficacy, &amp; bad tendency of pushing <orgName type="#USmilitary">Military</orgName> Impresses too far and the impracticability of keeping the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Army</orgName> supplied without it, or money, to pay the transportation I drew for 9000 dollars of the Sum sent on by the State of <location><region>Massachusetts</region></location> for payment of their <orgName type="#USmilitary">Troops</orgName>; and placed it in the hands of the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">QM General</roleName> with the most positive orders to apply it solely to this purpose.</p>
         <p>Fixed with <persName>Ezekiel Cornell Esqr.</persName> a member of the <orgName type="#political">Board of War</orgName> (then on a tour to the Eastward to inspect some of the Armoury’s &amp;ca;.) on certain articles of Cloathing—arms and <orgName type="#USmilitary">Military</orgName> Stores which might be sent from hence to supply the wants of the Southern Army.
            <persName>Major Talmadge</persName> was requested to press the C——s Senr. &amp; Junr. to continue their correspondence and was authorized to assure the elder C—— that he should be repaid the Sum of 100 Guineas, or more, with interest; provided he advanced the same for the purpose of defraying the expence of the correspondence, as he had offered to do.</p>
         <p><persName>Colo. Dayton</persName> was also written to, and pressed to establish a correspondence with <placeName>New York</placeName>, by way of <location><settlement>Elizabeth Town</settlement></location> for the purpose of obtaining intelligence of the <orgName type="#Britain">Enemys</orgName> movemts. and designs; that by a comparison of Accts. proper &amp; just conclusions may be drawn.</p>
         <p><date>May 2d.</date> No occurrence of note. A very fresh and steady gale of Wind all day from the So. East. Upon its shifting (about dusk) it blew violently, &amp; continued boisterous through the Night or greatest part of it.</p>
         <p> <date>4th.</date> A Letter of the <persName>Baron de Steuben</persName>’s from <placeName>Chesterfield Court House Virga.</placeName> dated the <date>21st.</date> Ulto. informs that 12 of the <orgName type="#Britain">Enemys</orgName>Vessels but with what <orgName type="#USmilitary">Troops </orgName>he knew not, had advanced up James River as high as <location><settlement>Jamestown</settlement></location>—that few <orgName type="#USmilitary">Militia</orgName> were in arms and few arms to put into their hands—that he had moved the public Stores from <location><settlement>Richmond</settlement></location> &amp;ca;. into the interior Country.</p>
         <p> A Letter from the <persName>Marqs. de la Fayette</persName>, dated at <location><settlement>Alexandria</settlement></location> on the <date>23d</date>., mentioned his having commenced his march that day for <location><settlement>Fredericksburg</settlement></location>—that desertion had ceased, &amp; that his detachment were in good Spirits.</p>
         <p> <date>5th.</date> Accounts from <persName>Brigadr. Genl. Clinton</persName> at <location><settlement>Albany</settlement></location>, dated the <date>30th.</date> ulto. &amp; 1st. Inst., filled me with anxious fears that the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Garrison</orgName> of <placeName>fort Schuyler</placeName> would be obliged to evacuate the Post for want of Provisions and that a Mutiny in the other <orgName type="#USmilitary">Troops</orgName> was to be apprehended. In consequence of this alarming information, I directed the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Q. M. Gl.</roleName> to send 50 Barls. of flour &amp; the like qty. of Salted Meat immy. up for the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Garrison</orgName> of <placeName>Fort Schuyler</placeName>—but of the latter there being only 24 in Store, no more could be sent.</p>
         <p> <date>6th.</date> <persName>Colo. Menonville,</persName> one of the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Adjutt. Generals</roleName> in the <orgName type="#military">French Army</orgName> came to Head Quarters by order of <persName>Count de Rochambeau </persName>to make arrangements for supplying the <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> of <persName>His Most Christian Majesty</persName> with certain provisions contracted for by <persName>Doctr. Franklin</persName>. This demand, tho’ the immediate compliance with it, was not insisted upon, comports illy with our circumstances; &amp; is exceedingly embarrassing.</p>
         <p>The <roleName type="#MilOfficer">D[eputy] Q[uarter] M[aster]</roleName> at <placeName>Sussex C[our]t House</placeName>, [360] conceiving that the Provision Magazine, &amp; other stores at that place were exposed to a surprize, and in danger of being destroyed by the <orgName type="#NativeTribe">Indians</orgName> &amp; Tories who were infesting the Settlement at Minisink, I directed<persName> Colo. Dayton</persName> to send a guard there from the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Jersey Brigade</orgName> near <location><settlement>Morristown</settlement></location>.</p>
         <p> <persName>Mr. John Flood </persName>(at present a liver at lower Salem) whom I had sent for to obtain from him an acct. of the Harbours in the Sound from Frogs point Eastward, arrived; and gave the information wch. is filed in my Office.</p>
         <p> Other letters arriving this Evening late (more expressive of the wants of the <orgName type="#USmilitary">York Troops</orgName> at <location><settlement>Albany</settlement></location>, &amp; the Posts above) I ordered 100, out of 131 Barrls. of Flour which were in Store, to be immediately sent up; &amp; again called upon the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Q. M. Genl.</roleName> in the most pointed terms to send active men to forward on, by every means they could devise, the Salted provs. in <location><settlement>Connecticut;</settlement></location> &amp; flour from Sussex Ct. Ho. &amp;ca;.</p>
         <p> That the States might not only know our Wants, which my repeated &amp; pressing letters had recently, &amp; often communicated, but, if possible, be impressed with them and adopt some mode of Transporting it to the Army, I resolved to send <persName>Genl. Heath </persName>(2d. Offr. in Commd.) to make to the respective legislatures East of York State, pointed representations; &amp; to declare explicitly that unless measures are adopted to supply transportation, it will be impossible to subsist &amp; keep the <orgName type="#military">Troops </orgName>together.</p>
         <p> <date> 7th.</date> The Wind which blew with great force from the So. East the last two days was accompanied this day by incessant Rain and was a most violent Storm &amp; is supposed to have done damage to Ships on the Coast.</p>
         <p><date>9th.</date> Went to the Posts at <placeName>West point</placeName>, and found by enquiry of <persName>General Heath</persName>, that all the Meat deposited in the advanced redoubts for contingent purposes would not, if served out, serve the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Army</orgName> two days—that the <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> had drawn none that day &amp; that none remained in the common Magazine.</p>
         <p><date>10th.</date> The <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Q. M. Genl.</roleName> representing, that it was not in his power to get the Salt Meat of <location><settlement>Connecticut</settlement></location> transported—even for the Money that was put into his hands for this purpose—the people now alledging that they had no forage—when the badness of the roads was an excuse when they were called upon by the Executive of their State in the Month of March and that nothing but <orgName type="#military">Military</orgName> force could affect the transport for our present wants. Parties were ordered out accordingly and the Officers commanding them directed to receive their Instructions from him.</p>
         
         <p>[362]<date>11th.</date> <persName>Major Genl. Heath</persName> set out this day for the Eastn. States, provided with Instructions, and letters couched in strong terms—representing the distresses of the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Army</orgName> for want of provisions and the indispensable necessity of keeping up regular supplies by the adoption of a plan, which will have system &amp; permanency in’t.</p>
         <p>This day also I received advice from <persName>Colo. Dayton</persName> that 10 Ships of the line, and 3 or 4000 <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> had sailed from <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location>. The intelligence was immediately communicated to Congress, and to the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">French Genl.</roleName> &amp; <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Admiral</roleName> at <location><region>R. Isld</region></location>.</p>
         <p> <date>12th.</date> <persName>Colo. Dayton</persName>’s intelligence, so far as respected the Sailing of <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName>, was confirmed by two sensible deserters from <location><settlement>Kingsbridge</settlement></location>; which place they left yesterday Morning at two Oclock. They add the detachment consisted of the <orgName type="#military">Grenadrs.</orgName> (Bh.)—the <orgName type="#military">Corps. of Anspach</orgName> (two Battalions) &amp; <orgName type="#military">the 37th. &amp; 43d. British regiments</orgName>, amounting, as is supposed, to about 2000 Men under the Command of <persName>Majr. Genl. Redeisel</persName>.</p>
         <p> <date>13th.</date> Received Letters from <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> advising me of the arrival of his Son &amp; from <persName>Count de Barras</persName> informing me of his appointment to the Command of the <orgName type="#military">French Squadron</orgName> at <location><region>Rhode Island</region></location>—both solliciting an Interview with me as soon as possible. Appointed, in answer, <date>Monday the 21st</date>. Inst. &amp; Wethersfield, as the time &amp; place of Meeting.</p>
         <p> <date>14th.</date> About Noon, intelligence was recd. from <persName>Genl. Patterson</persName> at<placeName> West point</placeName>, that the <orgName type="#Britain">Enemy</orgName> were on the No. side of Croton in force—that <persName>Colo. Green</persName>,<persName> Majr. Flag</persName>, &amp; some other officers with 40 or 50 Men were surprized &amp; cut off at the Bri⟨dg⟩e &amp; that <persName>Colo. Scammell</persName> with the <orgName type="#USmilitary">New Hampshire Troops</orgName> had Marched to their assistance. I ordered the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Connecticut Troops </orgName>to move in &amp; support those of <location><region>New Hampshire</region></location>.</p>
         <p> In the evening, information was brot. that the <orgName type="#Britain">enemy</orgName> (consisting of about 60 horse, &amp; 140 Infantry) had retreated precipitately &amp; that several of our <orgName type="#USmilitary">Soldiers</orgName> had been inhumanly murdered.</p>
         
         <p>[365]<date>15th.</date> Information, dated 12 oclock yesterday reports 15 Sail of Vessels &amp; a number of Flatboats to be off <placeName>Fort Lee</placeName>. Ordered a detachment of 200 Men to March immediately to support the Post at Dobbs’s. ferry—countenance the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Militia</orgName>, &amp; cover the Country in that Neighbourhood.</p>
         <p> Intelligence from C—— Senr., dated 729—a detachment is expected to Sail tomorrow from <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location>, &amp; said to consist of the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Anspach Troops’s 43d. B. Regiment</orgName>, remainder of the <orgName type="#USmilitary">76th., 80th., 17th. Dragoons, &amp; Infantry</orgName> of the same—to be conveyed by 7 Ships of the line, 2 fifties, &amp; 3 forty fours which are to cruize of the Capes of <location><region>Virginia</region></location>. He gives it as the opinion of C—— Junr. that the above detachmt. does not exceed 2000 Men—that not more than 4000 remain—wch. is only (he adds) to be accounted for on the supposition of their expecting a reinforcement immediately from <orgName type="#nation">Europe</orgName>.</p>
         <p> <date>16th.</date> Went to the Posts at <placeName>West point</placeName>. Received a particular acct. of the surprize of <persName>Colo. Green</persName> &amp; the loss we sustained which consisted of himself &amp; <persName>Major (Flag)</persName> killed—three officers &amp; a Surgeon taken prisoners (the latter &amp; two of the former wounded)—a <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Sergeant</roleName> &amp; 5 R[ank] &amp; F[ile] killed—5 left wounded &amp; 33 made Prisoners &amp; missing—in all 44 besides Officers.</p>
         <p>The report of the number of Shipping &amp;ca;. at <placeName>Fort Lee</placeName> was this day contradicted in part—the number of Vessels being reduced, &amp; said to be no higher than Bulls ferry. In consequence of this intelligence <persName>Lt. Colo. Badlam</persName> who marched with the detachment of 200 Men pursuant to the order of Yesterday &amp; had reached Stony point halted—but was directed not to return till the designs of the enemy were better understood.</p>
         <p><date> 17th.</date> Received a letter from <persName>Captn. Lawrence</persName>, near <location><settlement>Dobbss ferry</settlement></location>, informing me that abt. 200 Refugees were building a block house &amp; raising other works at <placeName>Fort Lee</placeName>. Order’d the detachment [366] [367] which had halted at <location><settlement>Kings Ferry</settlement></location> &amp; another forming under <persName>Colo. Scammel</persName> to advance down &amp; endeavour to annoy, if they could not prevent them.</p>
         <p> A Letter from <persName>Genl. Foreman</persName> of Monmouth (dated the 14th. Instt.) informs me that the <orgName type="#Britain">British fleet</orgName> from <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location> consisting of Seven Ships of 60 Guns &amp; upwards—12 large Transport Vessels, &amp; 10 topsail Schooners &amp; Sloops made Sail from Sandy hook the 12th., with the wind at So. East. but veering round to the Southward, &amp; Westward, it returned within the hook &amp; lay there till 10 o’clock next day when it again Sailed. By two oclock it was clear of the hook and steering Southward.</p>
         <p><date>18th.</date> Received Letters from Generals <persName>Schuyler</persName> and <persName>Clinton</persName> giving an acct. of the threatened Invasion of the Northern Frontier of this State from <orgName type="#nation">Canada</orgName>, and of the unfavourable prospects from Vermont and of the destruction of the Post of <placeName>Fort Schuyler</placeName>—the indefensible State of the Works occasioned thereby &amp; submitting for considn. the propriety of removing the <orgName type="#military">Garrison</orgName> to the <orgName type="#military">German Flatts</orgName> which he (that is Clinton) was requested to do if it appear’d to be the sense of the <roleName type="#USpolitical">Governor</roleName> &amp; other principal Gentn. of the State that it would be eligable.</p>
         <p>Set out this day for the Interview at <location><settlement>Weathersfield</settlement></location> with the <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> &amp; <persName>Admiral Barras</persName>. Reached <placeName>Morgans Tavern</placeName> 43 Miles from <location><settlement>Fishkill Landing</settlement></location> after dining at <persName>Colo. Vandebergs</persName>.</p>
         <p> <date>19th</date>. Breakfasted at Litchfield—dined at Farmington &amp; lodged at <location><settlement>Weathersfield </settlement></location>at the House of <persName>Joseph Webb Esqr.</persName> (the Quarters wch. were taken for me &amp; my Suit).</p>
         <p><date>20th.</date> Had a good deal of private conversation with <persName>Govr. Trumbull</persName> who gave it to me as his opinion that if any important offensive operation should be undertaken he had little doubt of our obtaining Men &amp; Provision adequate to our wants. In this opinion <persName>Colo. Wadsworth</persName> &amp; others concurr’d.</p>
         
         <p>[369]<date>21st.</date> The <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> with the <persName>Chevr. de Chastellux</persName> arrived about Noon. The appearance of the <orgName type="#Britain">British Fleet</orgName> (under <persName>Adml. Arbuthnot</persName>) off <placeName>Block Island</placeName> prevented the attendance of the <persName>Count de Barras</persName>.</p>
         <p><date> 22nd.</date> Fixed with <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> upon a plan of Campaign—in Substance as follows. That the <orgName type="#military">French Land force</orgName> (except 200 Men) should March so soon as the <orgName type="#military">Squadron</orgName> could Sail for <location><settlement>Boston</settlement></location>—to the North River &amp; there, in conjunction with the American, to commence an operation against <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location> (which in the present reduced State of the <orgName type="#military">Garrison</orgName> it was thought would fall, unless relieved; the doing which wd. enfeeble their Southern operations, and in either case be productive of capital advantages) or to extend our views to the Southward as circumstances and a Naval superiority might render more necessary &amp; eligable. The aid which would be given to such an operation in this quarter—the tardiness with which the Regiments would be filled for any other—the insurmountable difficulty &amp; expence of Land transportation—the waste of Men in long marches (especially where there is a disinclination to the Service—objections [370] to the climate &amp;ca;.) with other reasons too numerous to detail, induced to this opinion. The heavy Stores &amp; Baggage of the <orgName type="#military">French Army</orgName> were to be deposited at <location><settlement>Providence</settlement></location> under Guard of 200 Men (before mentioned) &amp; <placeName>Newport Harbour</placeName> &amp; Works were to be secured by 500 <orgName type="#USmilitary">Militia</orgName>.</p>
         <p>  <date>23d.</date> <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> set out on his Return to <location><settlement>Newport</settlement></location>, while I prepared and forwarded dispatches to the <roleName type="#USpolitical">Governors</roleName> of the four <location><region>New England</region></location> States calling upon them in earnest &amp; pointed terms, to compleat their <orgName type="#USmilitary">Continental Battalions</orgName> for the Campaign, at least, if it could not be done for the War or 3 Years—to hold a body of <orgName type="#USmilitary">Militia</orgName> (according to the Proportion given them) ready to march in one Week after being called for and to adopt some effectual mode to supply the <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> when assembled with Provisns. &amp; Transportation.</p>
         <p> I also sollicited the <roleName type="#USpolitical">Governors</roleName> of the States of<location> <settlement>Massachusetts</settlement></location> &amp; <location><settlement>Connecticut</settlement></location>earnestly for a Loan of Powder &amp; the means of Transporting it to the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Army</orgName>.</p>
         
         <p>[371] A Letter from <persName>Genl. St. Clair</persName> came to hand with accts. of an apparent intention of the <orgName type="#Britain">enemy</orgName> to evacuate <location><region>New York</region></location>.</p>
         <p><date>24th.</date> Set out on my return to <location><settlement>New Windsor</settlement></location>—dined at <location><settlement>Farmington </settlement></location>and lodged at <location><settlement>Litchfield</settlement></location>.</p>
         <p> <date>25th.</date> Breakfasted at Squire Cogswells—dined at <persName>Colo. Vandeburgs</persName> &amp; reached head Quarters about Sunset where I found letters from <persName>Generls. Schuyler</persName> &amp; <persName>Clinton</persName>, full of uncertain information respecting the enemys landing at Crown point &amp; intention to penetrate on the Hudson &amp; Mohawk Rivers. This uncertainty respects the number, not the fact—the latter seeming to be beyond a doubt. In consequence of this information I ordered the <orgName type="#USmilitary">Companies of Vanscaicks Regiment</orgName> at <placeName>West point</placeName> to hold themselves in readiness to Move at an hours warning.</p>
         <p> <date>26th.</date> Received a Letter from the Honble. <persName>Jno. Laurens Minister</persName> from the <orgName type="#nation">United States of America</orgName> at the <orgName type="#political">Court of Versailles</orgName>—informing me that the Sum of 6,000,000 of Livres was granted as a donation to this Country—to be applied in part to the purchase of Arms—Cloaths &amp;ca;. for the <orgName type="#USmilitary">American Troops</orgName> and the [372] ballance to my orders, &amp; draughts at long sight and that a Fleet of 20 Sail of the Line was on its departure for the <placeName>West Indies</placeName> 12 of which were to proceed to this Coast where it was probable they might arrive in the <date>Month of July.</date> He also added that the <orgName type="#political">Courts of Petersbg</orgName>. &amp; Vienna had offered their Mediation in settling the present troubles wch. the <persName>King of France</persName>, tho’ personally pleas’d with, could not accept without consulting his Allies. A Letter from <persName>Doctr. Lee</persName>—inclosing extracts of one from his Brother <persName>Wm. Lee Esqr</persName>. dated the <date>20th. of Feby</date>. holds out strong assurances of Peace being restored in the course of this Yr.</p>
         <p> <date>28th.</date> The <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Commanding Officer of Artillery</roleName> &amp; the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">chief Engineer</roleName> were called upon to give in estimates of their wants for the intended operation against <location><region>New York</region></location>. The intention of doing this was also disclosed to the <roleName type="#MilOfficer">Q. M. General</roleName> who was desired to give every attention toward the Boats, that a number of them might be prepared; &amp; provide other matters necessary to such an undertaking—especially those things which might be called for by the Artillery, &amp; the Engineering departments.</p>
         <p><date>31st.</date> A Letter from <persName>Count de Rochambeau</persName> informed me that the <orgName type="#Britain">British fleet</orgName> had left Block Island—that <persName>Adml. de Barras</persName> would Sail with the first fair Wind for <location><settlement>Boston</settlement></location> (having 900 of his Soldiers on Board to Man his fleet) and that he should commence his March as soon as possible, but would be under the necessity of Halting a few days at <location><settlement>Providence</settlement></location>.</p>
         <p> A Letter from <persName>Major Talmage</persName>, inclosing one from C—— Senr. &amp; another from S. G. dated the <date>27th</date>. were totally silent on the subject of an evacuation of <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location>; but speak of an order for Marching the <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> from <location><settlement>Long Island</settlement></location> and the Countermand of it after they had commenced their March; the cause for either they could not assign. Neither C. Senr. nor S. G. estimate the <orgName type="#Britain">Enemys</orgName> regular force at <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location> or its dependencies at more than 4500 men including the New Levies; but C—— says it is reported that they can command five &amp; some add 6,000 Militia &amp; refugees. S. G. disposes of the <orgName type="#Britain">Enemys</orgName> force as follow.</p>
         <p> At <placeName>Fort Washington</placeName> &amp; towards <location><settlement>New York</settlement></location>—<orgName type="#military">2 Hessn. Regts.</orgName>	2
            <placeName>Laurel Hill—Fort George.</placeName> <orgName type="#military">57th B</orgName>.	1
            <placeName>Haerlam</placeName>—at a place called <placeName>Laurel Hill</placeName>—<orgName type="#military">38 Do.</orgName>	1
            At <placeName>Hornes hook,</placeName> &amp; towds. the City—<orgName type="#military">22d. &amp; 42d. B. Regts</orgName>.	2
            In the City <orgName type="#military">Hessian Regimts</orgName>.	2
            On <placeName>Staten Island</placeName>	2
            Total on this Isld. . . . . . 1200	
            On <placeName>Long Island</placeName>	
            <orgName type="#military">1st. B. Grenadrs</orgName>. . . . <placeName>New Town	</placeName>1
            2d. . . . . Ditto . . . <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>	1
            <persName>Worms Hessian Yagers </persName>(called by him 6 or 700) No. side of the Plains	1
            <persName>Light Dragns</persName>. . . . <orgName type="#military">17th. Regt.</orgName> at <placeName>Hempstead Plains</placeName>	1
            <persName>Loyds Neck</persName>—detachmets. from <orgName type="#military">New Corps Abt. 6, or 700</orgName>	14
            The detachment which left Sandy hook the 13th Instt. according to the<persName> S. G.’s</persName> acct.—consisted of the <orgName type="#military">Troops</orgName> on the other side [375] —though it is thought he must be mistaken in naming the <orgName type="#military">46th. &amp; 86th. Regimts</orgName>.—the first of them being a convention Regimt. and the other not in America. By Accts. from Deserters the <orgName type="#military">37th. Regt.</orgName> went with the detachment and must be in place of the <orgName type="#military">46th. as the 80th</orgName>. must be that of the 86th.
            suppos’d
            <orgName type="#military">43 British Regiments 300</orgName>	
            <orgName type="#military">Anspach—2 Battalions	700</orgName>
            part of the <orgName type="#military">86th.	150</orgName>
            part of the <orgName type="#military">46th.	150</orgName>
            <orgName type="#military">Hessian Yagers—abt.	150</orgName>
            1450
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>